Guide to the John Waddell Collection of Mining Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John Waddell Collection of Mining Papers
1896-1914
WA MSS S-3049
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
The collection consists of manuscript and printed letters, prospectuses, and brochures describing oil and mining investment opportunities in Colorado, Alaska, and Arizona. The bulk of the collection concerns mining ventures in Colorado, and particularly well-represented companites include the Crosby-Ehrich Syndicate, the Jack Pot Mining Company, and Tucker, Ballard, and Company of Colorado Springs; the Ramsay C. Bogy Investment Company of Denver; and the Gold Coin Mining and Leasing Company of Victor. The bulk of the materials is addressed to John Waddell and was collected by him as a prospective investor in oil and mining ventures. Some of letters, prospectuses, and reports include pictorial representations of oil fields. Printed maps of the mines of the Pinnacle Junior Mining Company of Colorado Springs and Alaska's Klondike River Valley are also included.
Waddell, John, active 1896-1914
Biographical / Historical
John Waddell of Orono, Ontario, mining investor and stock speculator.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of manuscript and printed letters, prospectuses, and brochures describing oil and mining investment opportunities in Colorado, Alaska, and Arizona. The bulk of the collection concerns mining ventures in Colorado, and particularly well-represented companites include the Crosby-Ehrich Syndicate, the Jack Pot Mining Company, and Tucker, Ballard, and Company of Colorado Springs; the Ramsay C. Bogy Investment Company of Denver; and the Gold Coin Mining and Leasing Company of Victor. The bulk of the materials is addressed to John Waddell and was collected by him as a prospective investor in oil and mining ventures. Some of letters, prospectuses, and reports include pictorial representations of oil fields. Printed maps of the mines of the Pinnacle Junior Mining Company of Colorado Springs and Alaska's Klondike River Valley are also included.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Colorado Springs, 1896-1914. II. Cripple Creek, 1896-1906. III. Denver, 1879-1913. IV. Victor, 1896-1909. V. Alaska, Arizona, Georgia, and Minnesota, 1898-1914.
Investments -- United States; Gold mines and mining -- Colorado; Mineral rights -- Colorado; Mines and mineral resources -- Colorado; Mines and mineral resources -- Colorado -- Cripple Creek Region; Alaska -- Yukon -- Klondike River Valley -- Maps; Colorado -- Commerce; Colorado -- Cripple Creek Region -- Maps; Drawing -- United States -- 20th Century; Promotional materials -- United States -- 20th Century; Prospectuses -- United States -- 20th Century; Maps (documents) -- Colorado -- Colorado Springs; Maps (documents) -- Alaska -- Klondike River Valley (Yukon); Waddell, John, active 1896-1914; Crosby-Ehrich Syndicate; Jack Pot Mining Company; Tucket, Ballard, and Company; Ramsay C. Bogy Investment Company; Gold Coin Mining and Leasing Company
- Colorado Springs, 1896-1914; Series I
  - The Beaver Bell Gold Mining Company annual meeting notice, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colorado Springs Gazette, 1900-1900 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colorado Springs Board of Trade & Mining Exchange printed card giving commissions and board lots, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Colorado Springs Mining Stock Association printed card listing members names and commissions, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colorado Springs Mining Stock Association, Official Summary of Reports of Listed Companies, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Colorado Springs Mining Stock Association, The Authentic Mining Stock Reporter, 1897-1897 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Crosby-Ehrich Syndicate correspondence, stock purchase receipts, and reports, 1899-1902, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Delaney & Delaney, Banker & Broker letters, 1904-1908 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Elkton Consolidated Mining & Milling Company stockholder's notices, 1898-1898 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The El Paso Consolidated Gold Mining Company stockholder's materials, 1907-1908 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Gardner & Company letters, reports, and purchase receipts, 1897-1914
  - J.J. Hagerman letter referring to the Bull Mountain Gold Mining Company and its history, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Hamlet Mining & Milling Company prospectus issued by Gardner & Company, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Hermosa Gold Mining Company copies of articles taken from the Colorado Springs Gazette and distributed by the Crosby-Ehrich Syndicate to their clients with a limited offer for stock purchase, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Home Gold Mines Company letters, report, and clipping, 1910-1914 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Isabella Gold Mining Company letters and meeting notice, 1897-1900, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jack Pot Mining Company letters and stockholder's material, 1900-1905 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Kimberly Gold Mining Company letter from Company Secretary requesting decision on receipt of dividends in cash or El Paso Consolidated Gold Mining Company stock, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - C. F. Kjellander & Co., Brokers letter referring to commission rate for the Board of Trade, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - S. J. Mattocks, mining broker, letter transmitting a certificate for Index, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Marr & Middagh letter of introduction to prospective clients giving references and referring to their forthcoming Cripple Creek Mine Handbook, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Molly Dwyre Gold Mining Company letters to stockholders, 1901-1902 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Moon-Anchor Gold Mining Company letters, 1898-1900 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - L.C. Nickerson & Company Brokers, two autograph manuscript letters written by L. C. Nickerson to John Waddell attempting to convince him to finance a mining property in Colorado, 1898- (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Out West Trading Company circular letter written to stockholders regarding a quarterly dividend and an invitation to purchase shares in the company, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Frank H. Pettingell, Banker & Broker letter offering 50,000 shares for sale in The Santa Rosa Gold Mining Company, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Pinnacle Junior Mining Company letters, prospectus, and map, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Tucker, Ballard & Company, Brokers letters, stock purchase receipts, and stockholder's material, 1898-1908 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - United Gold Mines Company letters and company description, 1905, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Western Financing Corporation and The Woods Investment Company letters and market report, 1900-1914 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Cripple Creek, 1896-1906; Series II
  - The Cripple Creek Times letter regarding a subscription, signed by G.S. Hoag, Manager, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Gilpin & Cripple Creek Gold Mining Company report on the development of the Atlanta Mine, located on Bull Hill, Cripple Creek by the Manager A. B. Harmani, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Fulton-Marguerite Mining Company prospectus prepared by The Crosby-Ehrich Syndicate detailing properties, acreage and title, capitalization and treasury reserves, plans for development and subscription stock, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Fulton Marguerite Mining Company letter regarding tax litigation and a stockholder assessment, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Waverly Gold Mining & Milling Company prospectus issued by The Ramsay C. Bogy Investment Co. outlining the company's holdings and presenting a report on the Peg-Leg Mining Claim, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Denver, 1879-1913; Series III
  - The Anaconda Mining Company letter and report, 1901-1901 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Beall Investment Company, Stock Brokers, letters and shareholder's material, 1897-1898 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Cripple Creek Madonna company description and stock offer written by The Ramsay C. Bogy Investment Company, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Gardner, Kirton & Company, Investment Brokers, letter to the stockholders of Jack Pot Mining Company seeking an option on all stock and market report to potential investors detailing some mining companies, 1909-1909 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Gardner-Stybr Investment Company, Investment Brokers, letters referring to brokerage fees and special information regarding the El Paso Consolidated Gold Mining Company, 1913-1913 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Johnson, Lute H., letter promoting the Seven Troughs Metals Company, a Nevada Company, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Little Nell Gold Mining Company prospectus written by The Ramsay C. Bogy Investment Company, with a map of the property location and newspaper clippings, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Ramsay C. Bogy Investment Company, Bankers and Brokers, letters and stock information, 1896-1901 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Ramsay C. Bogy Investment Company, Bankers and Brokers, letters and stock information, 1896-1901 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Torrey Exploration Company letter of introduction outlining management, capitalization and stock available for purchase, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Victor, 1896-1909; Series IV
  - Battle Mountain Consolidated Gold Mining Company abridged prospectus describing the property and presenting an assayer's report, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Gold Coin Mining & Leasing Company letters, 1897-1909 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Alaska, Arizona, Georgia, and Minnesota, 1898-1914; Series V
  - Golden Star Mining and Exploration Company of Duluth, Minnesota, shareholder correspondence concerning dividends and corporate and mine developments, 1899-1899 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Klondyke Gold Mining Company letter from H. Gardner, a Colorado mining promoter, describing the company's holdings, with a map of the Klondike on the verso, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Lexington Arizona Mining Company reports, 1913-1914 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Southern States Portland Cement Company correspondence concerning plant start-up, financial results, dividend payments, market conditions, strikes, and litigation regarding control of the company, 1903-1910 (Box 1, Folder 18)